Guide to the Little Ben Mining Company records 1892-1946
Montana Historical Society Library & Archives
Little Ben Mining Company records
1892-1946
Montana Historical Society Library & Archives Archives
MC 159
Little Ben Mining Company
3 linear feet
The Little Ben Mining Company was a Helena and Landusky, Montana, gold mining company, incorporated in 1932, to develop the Little Ben Quartz Lode which had been discovered in 1892. Records include general correspondence (1932-1945); financial records (1932-1945); legal documents, including an abstract of title (1892-1913); organizational materials (1932-1944) including minutes, stock books, etc.; and mint deposit reports (1933-1942).
The Little Ben Quartz Lode, located south of Harlem, Montana, was first discovered on January 1, 1892, by Robert M. Orman, and contained gold and silver and other precious metals. On August 17, 1893, Orman discovered the August Quartz Lode just north of the Little Ben. In April 1901 Orman deeded his interests in the Little Rockies Unorganized Mining District to Louis V. Bogy, in trust for Thomas C. Power and his heirs. The claim included the Little Ben, the Surprise, and the August. In February 1908 the claims were sold to Louis Goslin, who in turn deeded the properties to the newly incorporated August Mining Company in 1909. The federal government granted claims to the August and Little Ben mines in 1912. The next recorded change in ownership came in the early 1930s when the company was sold to Norman B. Holter of Helena, who reorganized the property as the Little Ben Mining Company. The new company was incorporated on June 3, 1932, with a capital stock of 120,000 no-par value shares. The directors of the company were T.B. Weir, George T. McGee, and James T. Finlen. John J. Mitchke served as the company's secretary-treasurer. The company kept offices in both Helena and Landusky and held over 540 acres of patented and unpatented claims. In 1933 the Little Ben Mining Company increased its capital stock to $600,000, divided into 120,000 shares with a par value of $5.00 each. Managers of the company's mines through the years included Frank B. Bryant, Frank H. MacPherson, P.A. Wickham, and G.C. Worthington. In 1940 the company began to encounter financial problems and in June 1942, all operations at the mines ceased. At that time the Board of Directors held a special meeting with the stockholders and their proxies and authorized the disposition of the property and assets of the corporation. Liquidation was started with the first of three payments to stockholders issued in December 1942. The final payment was issued in October 1944.
Records. 1892-1946. 3 linear feet. This collection consists primarily of financial records (1930-1944) of the Little Ben Mining Company including taxes, bank transactions, and dividend payments. In addition there are general correspondence, reports of ore deposits to the Denver mint, and organizational materials (1932-1944), including articles of incorporation, minutes, and stock certificates. There is also an abstract of title (1892-1913) and related documents for property owned by the August Mining Company, including the Little Ben Mine.
Arranged by series. Some material housed in Manuscript Volumes. See inventory below.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Library & Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Little Ben Mining Company
Phillips County (Mont.)
Gold mines and mining; Mines and mineral resources--Montana
Montana; Mines and Mineral Resources
Detailed Description of the Collection
- General Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include First National Bank & Trust Co of Helena, T. B. Weir, John E. Corette, N. B. Holter, Burt Moylan), 1932 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Charles Whitcomb, N. B. Holter, John J. Mitchke, G. C. Worthington, George T. McGee, Arthur Worsdell), 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include G. C. Worthington, John J. Mitchke, L. W. Shotwell, Hugh D. Galusha, C. B. Power, Arthur Worsdell, N. B. Holter, Frank H. MacPherson), 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Charles Whitcomb, Katie D. Whitcomb), 1934 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include P. A. Wickham), 1935 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Katherine B. Whitcomb, George T. McGee, T. B. Weir), 1936 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include P. A. Wickham, John J. Mitchke), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include P. A. Wickham, John E. Corett), 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include P. A. Wickham, John E. Corett), 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Hugh D. Galusha, James F. Finlen, George T. McGee), 1939 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include John J. Mitchke, N. B. Holter, P. A. Wickham, George T. McGee, Katie B. Whitcomb), 1940 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include N. B. Holter, John J. Mitchke, P. A. Wickham, John Huber, Ruby Gulch Mining Company), 1942 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Hugh D. Galusha, P. A. Wickham, John J. Mitchke, George T. McGee), 1943 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include John J. Mitchke), 1944-1945 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
- Court Papers
  - Holter v. McGee, et al.; Whitcomb v. McGee, et al. re stipulations for dismissal, 1932 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
- Financial Records
  - Bank account book: Frank B. Bryant, 1920-1942 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Bank account book: Little Ben Mining Company, 1932-1943 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Check registers (1-599), 1932-1938 (Box-folder 1 / 30-31)
  - Check registers (600-1079), 1939-1944 (Box-folder 2 / 1-2)
  - Charge slips, etc., 1933-1945 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Deposit slips: Little Ben Mining Company, 1933-1943 (Box-folder 2 / 4-8)
  - Deposit slips: Little Ben operating account, 1933-1942 (Box-folder 2 / 9-13)
  - Disbursements and receipts, 1942 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - Dividend payments and liquidating distributions (includes related correspondence), 1932-1944 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
  - Expense estimates, etc., 1932-1933 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
  - Financial cost statements, 1942 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
  - Invoice of equipment sold to the War Department, 1942 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
  - Receipts, 1932-1944, undated (Box-folder 2 / 19)
  - Taxes for 1930 (includes related correspondence), 1938 (Box-folder 2 / 20)
  - Taxes for 1932 (includes related correspondence), 1933 (Box-folder 2 / 21)
  - Taxes for 1933 (includes related correspondence), 1933-1935 (Box-folder 2 / 22)
  - Taxes for 1934 (includes return of Capital Stock Tax and related correspondence), 1933-1936 (Box-folder 2 / 23)
  - Taxes for 1935 (includes amended 1934 Montana Corporation License Tax and related correspondence), 1935-1936 (Box-folder 2 / 24)
  - Taxes for 1936 (includes related correspondence), 1936-1937 (Box-folder 2 / 25)
  - Taxes for 1937 (includes amended 1936 Montana Corporation License Tax and related correspondence), 1937-1939 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - Taxes for 1938 (includes related correspondence), 1938-1939 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
  - Taxes for 1939 (includes related correspondence), 1939-1940; 1942 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - Taxes for 1940 (includes amended 1939 Annual Information Return related correspondence), 1940-1941; 1943 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Taxes for 1941 (includes related correspondence), 1941-1942 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - Taxes for 1942 (includes related correspondence), 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Taxes for 1943 (includes related correspondence), 1943-1944 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Taxes for 1944 (includes related correspondence), 1944-1945 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - Taxes, 1933-1946 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
  - Unemployment compensation, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
- Legal Documents
  - Abstract of title: property of August Mining Company (includes Little Ben Mine), 1892-1913 (Box-folder 3 / 11)
  - Notes, etc. removed from abstract of title, 1892-1913 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
  - Certificate of dissolution, 1944 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1932-1944, undated (Box-folder 3 / 14)
- Organizational Records
  - Record book, 1932-1944 (Volume 1)
  - Articles, minutes, etc. removed from record book, 1932-1944 (Box-folder 3 / 15)
  - Stock certificate book, 1932-1944 (Box-folder 3 / 16)
  - Correspondence, etc. removed from stock certificate book, 1932-1944 (Box-folder 3 / 17)
  - Stock certificate book, 1933-1940 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - Correspondence, etc. removed from stock certificate book, 1933-1940 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
  - Stock certificate book, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 4 / 3)
- Reports
  - Memo of G. C. Worthington (re mining matters), 1933 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
  - Mint deposits (includes related correspondence), 1933-1938 (Box-folder 4 / 5-10)
  - Mint deposits (includes related correspondence), 1939-1942 (Box-folder 5 / 1-4)
- Miscellany
  - Inventory for power plant (Ruby Gulch), undated (Box-folder 5 / 5)
  - Notes, etc., 1932, undated (Box-folder 5 / 6)